<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Laszlo Treszkai - 2021-01-06</title><link href="https://www.treszkai.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.treszkai.com/feeds/2021-01-06.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.treszkai.com/</id><updated>2021-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Estimating personal COVID risk from population-level data</title><link href="https://www.treszkai.com/2021/01/06/microcovids/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Laszlo Treszkai</name></author><id>tag:www.treszkai.com,2021-01-06:/2021/01/06/microcovids/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If N people get infected per day in a country with susceptible population size S, then doing &amp;#8220;average&amp;#8221; activities has approximately an N/S risk of contracting it&amp;nbsp;daily.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In a nutshell:&lt;/strong&gt; If &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; people get infected per day in a country with susceptible population size &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;, then doing &amp;#8220;average&amp;#8221; activities has approximately an &lt;em&gt;N/S&lt;/em&gt; risk of contracting it on that&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.microcovid.org"&gt;microCOVID tool&lt;/a&gt; is great for estimating the chances of contracting &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19 during a given activity.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It does so by estimating the risk of transmission of various activities from literature data, combining this with an estimate of a met person being &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;#8217;m building a model which assumes that every citizen of the country acts exactly the same on a given day, which leads to the current infection rate. This means that if you do the same activities as &amp;#8220;everyone else&amp;#8221;, you&amp;#8217;ll have the same chance of getting infected as &amp;#8220;everyone&amp;nbsp;else&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caveat: these are all back-of-the-envelope calculations of an &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; simplistic&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;numbers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s run the numbers of this model &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=COVID-19_pandemic_in_Hungary&amp;amp;oldid=998710968"&gt;on Hungary, on January 6, 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New cases (average of 7 days):&amp;nbsp;1746/day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recovered:&amp;nbsp;180,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Population (&lt;sup id="fnref:kids"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:kids"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;):&amp;nbsp;9,770,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Susceptible (&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;): population - recovered =&amp;nbsp;9,590,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might argue&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that the actual case count is higher than those tested positive, but I assume cases which do not make the books are not severe enough to warrant a test. However, if your country doesn&amp;#8217;t seem to do enough tests (e.g. because the ratio of positive results per test is absurdly high), then the actual case count is surely&amp;nbsp;higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that for the &amp;#8220;average&amp;#8221; person, the chance of becoming infected is 1,746 / 9,590,000 / day ≈ 180 microCOVIDs /&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this &amp;#8220;average&amp;#8221; person does not refer to the most common person (the &lt;em&gt;mode&lt;/em&gt;) or the median; but literally, this Average Joe makes up the entire 10 million population of the country. In this model, everyone is equal. (And nobody more equal than the&amp;nbsp;others.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Act like this average person for an entire year (assume January 6 conditions all year long), and you have 6% chance of contracting the disease. (Because of course, every day of the year is&amp;nbsp;equal.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Comparing with&amp;nbsp;microCOVID&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://www.microcovid.org/?distance=sixFt&amp;amp;duration=480&amp;amp;interaction=oneTime&amp;amp;personCount=1&amp;amp;riskProfile=average&amp;amp;setting=indoor&amp;amp;theirMask=basic&amp;amp;topLocation=Hungary&amp;amp;voice=normal&amp;amp;yourMask=basic"&gt;tried to simulate&lt;/a&gt; the working day of the &amp;#8220;average&amp;#8221; citizen with the microCOVID tool. I did this using a one-time interaction&amp;nbsp;(daily):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for 8&amp;nbsp;hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;with 1&amp;nbsp;person&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at 6+ feet / 2+&amp;nbsp;meters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;indoors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cotton mask or bandana on me&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and on them&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having normal&amp;nbsp;conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds up to about 200 microCOVIDs each day. That&amp;#8217;s surprisingly close to my figure! I pinky-swear that I first picked these settings based on a gut feeling, and didn&amp;#8217;t adjust them to approximate 180&amp;nbsp;microCOVID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, changing the settings will move the risk away from 200 μCOVID/day. Grocery shopping and spouses/kids/relatives should also be added to the list. But the fact that these two models are in the same ballpark is good&amp;nbsp;validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The super easy method for pandemic risk&amp;nbsp;assessment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate the risk for the Average Citizen, by simply dividing the daily case increase&lt;sup id="fnref:avg"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:avg"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with the population size (whether that&amp;#8217;s a city or a country). Adjust this upwards if you think your country has insufficient testing&amp;nbsp;practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjust this with some factors for how you think your behavior compares with the average. Working from home? Divide by 5. Doing grocery shopping online? Divide by 2. Meeting a dozen people at the office every day? Multiply by five. I&amp;#8217;m just making these numbers up, but so can you. You should do this step &lt;em&gt;at the beginning&lt;/em&gt;, to minimize fooling&amp;nbsp;yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiply this by 365 to get the risk of contracting the virus in a year&lt;sup id="fnref:year"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:year"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. If you want to go fancy, use lower figures for the summer, higher ones while the graphs are skyrocketing. (Again, decide beforehand how to calculate this&amp;nbsp;step.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, smash a generous error bar on the result: say, plus or minus an order of&amp;nbsp;magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you live with 6% a chance of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt;-19 in the coming year? If not, then maybe you should scale back your activities. If your country&amp;#8217;s average risk is too low for you (for example, because you&amp;#8217;re young and live in New Zealand and are more likely to die in a car accident), then consider saying hello to the neighbors from a friendly&amp;nbsp;distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay safe. Wear a mask, wear a helmet, wear a safety&amp;nbsp;belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also introduces a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt; budget that you can allocate as you wish: if you target a 1% chance of contracting &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt; in a year, then you have 200 microCOVIDs allocated for each week. (0.01 / 50 = 0.0002.) Spend it wisely.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:kids"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until recently, kids did not play a significant role in the transmission and hospitalization, therefore minors could be (or could have been) deducted from the susceptible population.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:kids" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;microCOVID seems to compare the case count against the entire population. I count a recovered person as not immune to the virus.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hungary, the reported prevalence is 0.12%, but microCOVID uses an adjusted prevalence of 0.39%. This correction of 3x my model should use too.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should totally buy an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FFP&lt;/span&gt;-2 mask and fit it snugly to your face. If you wear it for long periods then buy a handful and rotate them daily. Dispose after one month. Adjust numbers as budget allows, but &lt;em&gt;buy one good mask&lt;/em&gt;. This does not constitute medical advice.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convince your employer to buy every employee an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FFP&lt;/span&gt;-2 mask. The less time you spend on sick leave, the better it is for them.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:avg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preferably averaged over the last 7 days.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:avg" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:year"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically, you should calculate 1 − (1−p)&lt;sup&gt;365&lt;/sup&gt;, but that&amp;#8217;s practically 365 × p. The overall calculation has much bigger errors anyway.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:year" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="2021-01-06"></category></entry></feed>